What is the difference between a series and
a parallel connection of resistors?
Here we consider a series and a parallel circuit
with three resistors with resistances R1,
R2 and R3.
A voltage U is applied to the resistors.
Difference #1:
Look at how the three resistors are connected
to each other.
In a series circuit, the positive pole of
the voltage source is connected to one single
resistor and the negative pole is also connected
to one single resistor.
The resistors in a series circuit form a chain.
In a parallel circuit, on the other hand,
you connect the positive pole of the voltage
source to three ends of the three resistors,
and you do the same with the negative pole.
Difference #2:
In a series connection, the same current flows
through all three resistors.
The total current I is therefore equal to
the current I1 through the first resistor,
but also equal to the current I2 and I3 through
the other two resistors.
In a parallel circuit, however, different
currents I1, I2 and I3 flow through the resistors.
The total current I is the sum of the individual
currents: I = I1 + I2 + I3
In a series circuit, you will measure a different
voltage across each resistor.
Voltage U1 across the first resistor.
U2 across the second resistor and U3 across
the third.
The total voltage U is the sum of the individual
voltages: U = U1 + U2 + U3.
In a parallel circuit, on the other hand,
you will measure the same voltage across all
three resistors.
The total voltage is therefore equal to the
voltage U1 between the ends of the first resistor,
but also equal to the voltage U2 and U3.
Difference #4:
The total resistance R of a series circuit
is the sum of the individual resistances:
R is equal to R1 + R2 + R3.
In a parallel circuit, however, the total
resistance R is not the sum of the individual
resistances.
The following relationship applies here: The
reciprocal total resistance "1 over R" is
the sum of the reciprocal resistances "1 over
R1" + "1 over R2 + "1 over R3".
Difference #5:
For the conductance values of the resistors,
it is the other way round.
The total conductance G of a parallel circuit
is the sum of the individual conductances
G1, G2 and G3.
And in a series circuit, the reciprocal conductance
"1 over G" is equal to "1 over G1" + "1 over
G2" + "1 over G3".